# Soumyabrata DEV

Contact Information The ADAPT Centre Room G31, O'Reilly Building

Dublin 2, Trinity College Dublin

Ireland

Executive Statement

I am a researcher with interests primarily in image processing, machine learning, and deep learning. Most specifically, I am interested in using these expertise in solving problems related to consumer digital media, remote sensing and earth sciences.

# Current Affiliation

# ADAPT Centre, Trinity College Dublin

July 2017 – till date

soumyabrata.dev@outlook.com

https://soumyabrata.github.io

Post-doctoral Researcher

Currently working with Prof. François Pitié and Declan McKibben, in an industry-affiliated research project of Huawei Ireland Research Centre.

- Developing state-of-the-art techniques for effective image- and video- analysis in consumer advertisement videos.
- Published our findings in leading conferences.

# National College of Ireland, Dublin

August 2018 – till date

Associate Faculty

- Currently lecturing a course in programming and data analytics.
- Supervising students for their Master of Science research projects.

# Education

# Nanyang Technological University (NTU) Singapore

2012 - 2017

Ph.D. in Electrical & Electronic Engineering

Thesis: 2D and 3D Image Analysis and Its Application to Sky/Cloud Imaging

CGPA: 4.08/5.0

# National Institute of Technology Silchar, India

2006 - 2010

Bachelor of Technology in Electronics & Communication Engineering

Graduated  $summa\ cum\ laude$  with highest honors and ranked 1 in class of 70

CGPA: 9.43/10.0

# Experience

# Nanyang Technological University Singapore

Singapore, Singapore

PhD Student

July 2012 – July 2017

Worked with Prof. Lee Yee Hui, NTU Singapore and Dr. Stefan Winkler, Principal Scientist, Advanced Digital Sciences Center (ADSC).

- Developed state-of-the-art image segmentation and image classification algorithms for cloud image analysis and earth observations.
- Created and released first large-scale cloud image datasets with manually annotated labels to the community.
- Published our findings in top-tier journals and conferences.

# École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

Lausanne, Switzerland

Visiting Student

July 2015 – December 2015

Worked with Prof. Martin Vetterli and Dr. Adam Scholefield during this exchange term.

- Devised algorithms with theoretical bounds for point localization in multi-camera setups with noisy camera poses.
- Provided a rigorous analysis of such localization problems in the task of cloud-base height reconstruction using ground-based sky cameras.

Ericsson India Gurgaon, India

Engineer - Network Consulting

July 2010 - July 2012

- Provided 2G frequency planning and optimization for metropolitan cities, and received excellent customer feedback.

- Developed heuristic processes and optimization techniques to streamline the 2G/3G network operations. Developed tool was subsequently included into Ericsson's tools and services portal.

# Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore

Bangalore, India

Research Intern

May 2009 - July 2009

Worked with Prof. Vinod Sharma during this internship period.

- Developed a high performance source-relay assignment scheme, denoted Timer based Adaptive Relay Selection Protocol (TARSeP) that efficiently improves the overall throughput in wireless 802.11 networks.
- Published our results in a journal of related area.

# Indian Institute of Technology Guwahati

Guwahati, India

Research Intern

May 2008 – June 2008

Worked with Prof. Harshal B. Nemade during this internship period.

- Designed a minimum off-time device for protecting refrigerator compressor after a brief power interruption.
- Developed a working prototype of the designed device using off-the-shelf components.

# Teaching National College of Ireland

Dublin

Associate Faculty

July 2018 - till date

- Currently lecturing a course on 'Programming for big data' for Higher Diploma in Science in Data Analytics for the term January 2019 May 2019.
- Lectured a course on H9PDA: Programming for Data Analytics, for degree in Masters in Cloud Computing for the term August 2018 December 2018.

### Trinity College Dublin, Ireland

Dublin

Teaching Assistant

January 2019 – till date

- Currently conducting the lab sessions of EEU44C08 Digital Image and Video Processing, for fourth year undergraduates of Trinity College Dublin, for the term January 2019 – May 2019.

# NTU Singapore Outreach Team

Singapore

Instructor

January 2015 - June 2017

- Reached out to pre-tertiary students with a passion for Science and Engineering, and received commendable appreciation from Ministry of Education, Singapore.
- Developed learning programmes (viz. Cantenna workshop & LED Cube workshop) that offered students an opportunity to appreciate STEM field education, under the tutelage of NTU professors and staffs.

# NTU Singapore Undergraduate Class

Singapore

Peer Tutor

2016 - 2017

Teaching Assistant

2014 - 2016

- Taught the course *EE2008*: Data Structures and Algorithms to 150+ students for Semester 1 AY 2014–15, and Semester 2 AY 2015-16 session.
- Received Best Teaching Award for the course.

#### Supervision National College of Ireland

Dublin

Supervisor

July 2018 - till date

- Supervised 3 students in their Master of Science (MSc) research thesis, in areas of machine learning and data analytics.

# Nanyang Technological University Singapore Mentor

Singapore

January 2013 – June 2017

- Mentored 14 students in their Final Year Projects (FYPs) and Nanyang Research Program (NRP) projects, in areas of image processing and remote sensing.

- Invited Talks Invited talk at the IEEE YP Symposium on Impact of Data Science in Healthcare, July
  - Invited talk at Machine Learning Dublin meetup to discuss our recent work on deeplearning based advert-creation system, developed in collaboration with Huawei Ireland Research Centre, June 2019.
  - Talk on the course 'Inside the Machine: An Introduction to Architecture, Parallelism & its Applications', at University College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland, May 2019.
  - Undergraduate research talk on 'Solving Interdisciplinary Problems Using Computer Vision', at Maynooth University, Co. Kildare, February 2019.
  - Research talk on 'Computer-Vision Solutions for Sensing Problems', at University of Dundee, Scotland, October 2018.
  - Talk on the course 'Inside the Machine: An Introduction to Architecture, Parallelism & Electronics', at Bucknell University, Lewisburg, PA, United States, July 2018.
  - Seminar on 'Developing Computer-Vision Solutions for Sensing Problems in Intelligent Systems', at University of Derby, United Kingdom, April 2018.
  - Talk on 'Ground-based Image Analysis for Solar Energy Applications' in Machine Learning Dublin meetup at The Innovation Academy TCD, August 2017.

#### Publications 2019

- S. Manandhar, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, Y. S. Meng, and S. Winkler, A Data-Driven Approach for Accurate Rainfall Prediction, IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing,
- F. Orlandi, A. Meehan, M. Hossari, S. Dev, D. O'Sullivan and T. Alskaif, Interlinking Heterogeneous Data for Smart Energy Systems, International Conference on Smart Energy Systems and Technologies (SEST), 2019.
- S. Dev, M. Hossari, M. Nicholson, K. McCabe, A. Nautiyal, C. Conran, J. Tang, W. Xu, and F. Pitié, Localizing Adverts in Outdoor Scenes, IEEE International Conference on Multimedia & Expo Workshops (ICMEW), 2019.
- S. Dev, M. Hossari, M. Nicholson, K. McCabe, A. Nautiyal, C. Conran, J. Tang, W. Xu, and F. Pitié, The ALOS Dataset for Advert Localization in Outdoor Scenes, Eleventh International Conference on Quality of Multimedia Experience (QoMEX), 2019.
- C. S. Nwosu(\*), S. Dev(\*), P. Bhardwaj, B. Veeravalli, and C. J. Deepu, Understanding Electronic Health Records for Stroke Prediction, 41st Annual International Conference of the IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society (EMBC), 2019 (\* Authors contributed equally).
- T. AlSkaif(\*), S. Dev(\*), L. Visser, M. Hossari, and W. van Sark, On the Interdependence and Importance of Meteorological Variables for Photovoltaic Output Power Estimation, 46th IEEE Photovoltaic Specialists Conference (PVSC), 2019 (★ Authors contributed equally).
- S. Dev, A. Nautiyal, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, CloudSegNet: A Deep Network for Nychthemeron Cloud Segmentation, IEEE Geoscience and Remote Sensing Letters, 2019.
- S. Dev, M. Hossari, M. Nicholson, K. McCabe, A. Nautiyal, C. Conran, J. Tang, W. Xu, and F. Pitié, The CASE Dataset of Candidate Spaces for Advert Implantation, International Conference on Machine Vision Applications (MVA), 2019.
- S. Dev, S. Manandhar, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Multi-label Cloud Segmentation Using a Deep Network, IEEE AP-S Symposium on Antennas and Propagation and USNC-URSI Radio Science Meeting, 2019.

- S. Manandhar(\*), S. Dev(\*), Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Predicting GPS-based PWV Measurements Using Exponential Smoothing, *IEEE AP-S Symposium on Antennas and Propagation and USNC-URSI Radio Science Meeting*, 2019 (\* Authors contributed equally).
- M. Hossari, S. Dev and J. D. Kelleher, TEST: A Terminology Extraction System for Technology Related Terms, 11th International Conference on Computer and Automation Engineering (ICCAE), 2019.

#### 2018

- M. Hossari(\*), S. Dev(\*), M. Nicholson, K. McCabe, A. Nautiyal, C. Conran, J. Tang, W. Xu, and F. Pitié, ADNet: A Deep Network for Detecting Adverts, 26th Irish Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Cognitive Science (AICS), 2018 (\* Authors contributed equally and arranged alphabetically.).
- A. Nautiyal(\*), K. McCabe(\*), M. Hossari(\*), S. Dev(\*), M. Nicholson, C. Conran, D. McKibben, J. Tang, X. Wei, and F. Pitié, An Advert Creation System for Next-Gen Publicity, European Conference on Machine Learning and Principles and Practice of Knowledge Discovery in Databases (ECM-PKDD), 2018 (\* Authors contributed equally and arranged alphabetically.).
- S. Dev(\*), T. AlSkaif(\*), M. Hossari, R. Godina, A. Louwen, and W. van Sark, Solar Irradiance Forecasting Using Triple Exponential Smoothing, *International Conference on Smart Energy Systems and Technologies (SEST)*, 2018 (\* Authors contributed equally).
- S. Manandhar(\*), S. Dev(\*), Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler and Y. S. Meng, Systematic Study of Weather Variables for Rainfall Detection, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)*, 2018 (\* Authors contributed equally).
- S. Manandhar, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, Y. S. Meng and S. Winkler, A Data-driven Approach to Detect Precipitation from Meteorological Sensor Data, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)*, 2018.
- F. Pitié, A. Nautiyal, S. Dev, M. Nicholsan, A. Abdelkader, K. McCabe, C. Conran, D. McKibben, An automatic system that identifies and locates the four corners of the advertising space in a video as a cloud service, *Patent Filed*, 2018.
- F. Pitié, A. Nautiyal, S. Dev, M. Nicholsan, A. Abdelkader, K. McCabe, C. Conran, D. McKibben, An algorithm that ranks candidate advertising spaces based on their quality and value, *Patent Filed*, 2018.
- S. Manandhar, Y. H. Lee, Y. S. Meng, F. Yuan and S. Dev, A Potential Low Cost Remote Sensing Using GPS Derived PWV, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)*, 2018.
- S. Dev, F. M. Savoy, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, High-Dynamic-Range Imaging for Cloud Segmentation, *Atmospheric Measurement Techniques (AMT)*, 2018.
- S. Manandhar(⋆), S. Dev(⋆), Y. H. Lee and Y. S. Meng, Analyzing Solar Irradiance Variation From GPS and Cameras, IEEE AP-S Symposium on Antennas and Propagation and USNC-URSI Radio Science Meeting, 2018 (⋆ Authors contributed equally).
- S. Manandhar, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee and Y. S. Meng, On the Importance of PWV in Detecting Precipitation, IEEE AP-S Symposium on Antennas and Propagation and USNC-URSI Radio Science Meeting, 2018.

### 2017

- S. Dev, F. M. Savoy, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Rough-set Based Visible Color Channel Selection, *IEEE Geoscience and Remote Sensing Letters*, vol. 14, no. 1, pp. 52-56, 2017.
- S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Color-based segmentation of sky/cloud images from ground-based cameras, *IEEE Journal of Selected Topics in Applied Earth Observations and Remote Sensing*, vol. 10, no. 1, pp. 231-242, Jan 2017.
- S. Dev, F. M. Savoy, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, DIY Sky Imager For Weather Observation: A complete guide to build a ground-based sky imager using off-the-shelf components

- with automatic cloud coverage computation, Students' Design Project Series: Sharing Experiences [SP Education], IEEE Signal Processing Magazine, Jan 2017.
- S. Dev, S. Manandhar, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Study of Clear Sky Models for Singapore, Proc. Progress In Electromagnetics Research Symposium (PIERS), 2017.
- S. Manandhar, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee and Y. S. Meng, Analyzing Cloud Optical Properties Using Sky Cameras, Proc. Progress In Electromagnetics Research Symposium (PIERS), 2017.
- S. Manandhar, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee and Y. S. Meng, Correlating Satellite Cloud Cover with Sky Cameras, *Proc. Progress In Electromagnetics Research Symposium (PIERS)*, 2017.
- S. Dev, F. Savoy, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Nighttime sky/cloud image segmentation, *IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP)*, 2017.
- F. Savoy, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Stereoscopic Cloud Base Reconstruction Using High-Resolution Whole Sky Imagers, *IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP)*, 2017.
- S. Dev, S. Manandhar, F. Yuan, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Cloud Radiative Effect Study Using Sky Camera, *IEEE AP-S Symposium on Antennas and Propagation and USNC-URSI Radio Science Meeting*, 2017.

#### 2016

- S. Dev, B. Wen, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Machine Learning Techniques and Applications For Ground-based Image Analysis, *IEEE Geoscience and Remote Sensing Magazine, Special Issue on Advances in Machine Learning for Remote Sensing and Geosciences*, vol. 4, no. 2, pp. 79-93, June 2016.
- S. Dev, S. Manandhar, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Detecting rainfall onset using sky images, TENCON 2016 - 2016 IEEE Region 10 Conference, 2016.
- S. Dev, F. M. Savoy, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Short-term prediction of localized cloud motion using ground-based sky imagers, TENCON 2016 - 2016 IEEE Region 10 Conference, 2016.
- S. Manandhar, F. Yuan, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee and Y. S. Meng, Weather radar to detect cloud occurrence level, TENCON 2016 2016 IEEE Region 10 Conference, 2016.
- S. Dev, F. M. Savoy, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Estimation of solar irradiance using ground-based whole sky imagers, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)*, 2016.
- F. M. Savoy, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Geo-referencing and stereo calibration of ground-based whole sky imagers using the sun trajectory, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)*, 2016.
- S. Manandhar, Y. H. Lee, S. Dev, GPS Derived PWV for rainfall monitoring, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)*, 2016.

#### 2015

- S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Categorization of Cloud Image Patches Using an Improved Texton-based Approach, *IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP)*, 2015
- S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Multi-level Semantic Labeling of sky/cloud images, *IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP)*, 2015.
- S. Dev, F. M. Savoy, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Design of low-cost, compact and weather-proof whole sky imagers for high-dynamic-range captures, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)*, 2015.
- F. M. Savoy, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Cloud base height estimation using high-resolution whole sky imagers, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)*, 2015.

• S. Dev, A. Ghasemi, M. Vetterli, A. Scholefield, Point localization in Multi-camera system, Doctoral internship report, École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne, Switzerland, 2015.

#### 2014

- S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Systematic Study of Color Spaces and Components for the segmentation of sky/cloud images, *IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP)*, 2014.
- S. Dev, F. M. Savoy, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, WAHRSIS: A low-cost, high-resolution whole sky imager with near-infrared capabilities, *Proc. IS&T/SPIE Infrared Imaging Systems: Design, Analysis, Modeling, and Testing*, 2014.

#### 2010

• S. Dev, Z.H. Choudhury, K. L. Baishnab, A. Nag, An efficient heap management technique with Minimum Fragmentation and Auto Compaction, *IEEE International Conference on Industrial and Information Systems*, 2010.

#### 2009

- S. Dev, Nischal S, An efficient partner assignment algorithm for improving the performance of 802.11 WLAN, *International Journal of Recent Trends in Engineering*, vol. 2, no. 6, Nov. 2009, Issue on Electrical and Electronics.
- S. Dev, Z. H. Choudhury, A randomized cryptographic algorithm and its simulation in C and MATLAB, with its hardware implementation in Verilog HDL, *IEEE Conference on Anti-Counterfeiting, Security and Identification*, Aug 2009.

# Skills Languages

Python, MATLAB, Perl.

# **Technologies**

TensorFlow, Keras, LATEX

# Expertise

image processing, machine learning, remote sensing, deep learning.

# Media Links

- Github: github.com/Soumyabrata
- Publons: publons.com/author/1307481/soumyabrata-dev
- Google Scholar: scholar.google.com.sg/citations?user=\_akXw8IAAAAJ

# Organization Xonkolpo

North-East India

Advisor

October 2013 – present

- Assisted in floating Xonkolpo: a non-profit initiative, along with other enthusiasts from Assam, India.
- Provided support and guidance, along with application materials for students, particularly from North-Eastern India to pursue studies in any Science, Technology, Engineering and Management (STEM) field.

#### NTU - Graduate Student Council

Singapore

Director April 2016 – March 2017
Director April 2015 – March 2016
Public Relations Officer May 2014 – March 2015

- Lead NTUGSC Career & Entrepreneurship committee that is primarily involved in organizing Career talks, Entrepreneurial talks and Industrial visits for the graduate students.
- Established long-term collaborations with NTU Career & Attachment Office (CAO) for our activities.

# **IEEE Young Professionals**

Chair Vice Chair Singapore November 2015 – November 2016 November 2014 – November 2015

November 2013 – October 2014

Executive Committee Member

- Lead the Singapore chapter of IEEE Young Professionals, and was primarily involved in facilitating young graduates to become world class professionals, enhancing their skills and establishing a strong and diverse professional network.
- Received best Affinity Group award from IEEE R10 section.

# **IEEE Student Chapter Silchar**

Silchar, India

Executive Committee Member

June 2008 – June 2010

- Responsible for the overall management of IEEE Student Chapter Branch affairs.

# Awards & Honors

- Awarded the Outstanding Academic Achievement award, by Technology Ireland, November 2018.
- Awarded the ADAPT Centre Directors Commercialisation Award 2018, in recognition of the contribution to Huawei Advert project.
- Recognition and appreciation for contribution as a tutor in the Peer Tutoring Scheme, NTU Singapore, AY 2016-17.
- IEEE Region-10 Young Professionals Affinity Group Award in recognition and appreciation of valued services and contributions, August 2016.
- Commendable Teaching Assistant Award for the AY 2014–15 by School of Electrical and Electronic Engineering, NTU Singapore, November 2015.
- Institute Silver Medal in Bachelor of Technology, National Institute of Technology Silchar, July 2010.

# References

Available on request.